Oyez Press Records
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Oyez Press Records.
1963-1987.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Oyez Press.
24 linear feet.
Founded in 1964 by Robert Hawley and Stevens van Strum, the Oyez Press initially produced a series of poetry broadsides by such notable figures as Robert Duncan, Robert Creeley, William Everson, Gary Snyder, and Charles Olson. Although van Strum left in 1968, Hawley continued on with the press in his spare time, eventually publishing over 80 books in addition to numerous keepsakes and broadsides, featuring authors such as David Meltzer, Josephine Miles, Lew Welch, Philip Lamantia, and many others. Oyez publications were highly regarded for the simplicity and elegance of their design; many were produced in collaboration with printer Graham Mackintosh.
MSS19980208
History
Robert Hawley was born in 1929 in Stockbridge, Wisconsin. He was a student at Black Mountain College in 1956, shortly before that institution closed its doors. Although he already had an M.A. in English and was an aspiring poet, Charles Olson discouraged him in this regard, but suggested to Hawley that he give publishing a try. By 1957, Hawley was in Berkeley, California, working as a bookseller specializing in Western Americana at the Holmes Book Company.
In 1964, Robert Hawley and Stevens van Strum started the Oyez Press by soliciting poems from noteworthy American poets to be published in a series of broadsides, effectively pioneering this publishing medium for poetry. This initial series consisted of ten broadsides, by such poets as William Everson (Brother Antoninus), Gary Snyder, Charles Olson, Michael McClure, and others. The first Oyez book was a collection of poetry by David Meltzer. It was during this period that Hawley began his business relationship with printer Graham Mackintosh. The Oyez poetry editions were well regarded for the simplicity and elegance of their designs. Although not all Oyez books were designed by Mackintosh, several of his designs did receive awards, including an edition of William Everson's Single Source that was selected as one of the 50 books of the year by the American Institute of Graphic Arts.
By the late 1960s, Oyez was publishing about ten books a year, even after Stevens van Strum departed the concern (around 1968), and even though Hawley continued with his day job at the Holmes Book Company. Although the print runs of Oyez books were limited at the cost of the books was kept low, the press did well so long as it had standing orders from universities and book stores with an interest in poetry and rare books. However, inventories began to mount and the cash reserves of the press began to dwindle in time. Hawley eventually turned over the distribution of the Oyez titles to Serendipity Books.
In 1978, Hawley opened his own book shop, the Ross Valley Book Company, in Albany, California (near Oakland). Even though the Oyez press continued to publish sporadically during the next few years, money troubles seriously limited the pace of Hawley's publishing projects. While a collection of poems by Samuel Charters was published in 1992, it is the only book-length project put out by Oyez since 1987. However, friends of the press have also received periodic keepsakes and pamphlets with the Oyez imprint over the years, a number of which are preserved in this collection.
Scope and Content
The collection consists largely of Robert Hawley's personal papers and records with regard to the Oyez Press from 1963 to 1988. The largest portion of the collection deals with project records of Oyez productions, including manuscripts, galleys, proofs, and production-specific correspondence. Additional correspondence preserved by Hawley documents his relationships with poets such as William Everson, Mary Fabilli, and David Meltzer. The press correspondence also provides a wide range of perspectives on the San Francisco Poetry scene in the late 1960s and early 1970s -- Hawley preserved many mailings from other publishers and announcements of poetry readings. Additionally, the collection contains business records including sales ledgers and receipts for a number of years prior to Oyez turning over distribution to a third party. The collection further consists of some of Robert Hawley's personal papers and one box of wood block engravings used for various Oyez projects.
The Dodd Center holds a comprehensive range of Oyez publications. The published versions of projects described in this collection are listed in HOMER, the Libraries online catalog.
Organization
Series I: Project Archives and Correspondence (undated, 1963-1987) contains project records for the majority of Oyez's publishing projects. Materials here include manuscripts, galleys, page proofs, and correspondence with printers and authors. Some personal correspondence with Oyez authors is included here, rather than in the next series.
Series II: Press Correspondence (undated, 1964-1986) is made up of press correspondence. Personal correspondence is sorted alphabetically, while additional mailings and ephemera are sorted by type. This series also contains a number of unsolicited manuscript submissions, which were never returned to their respective authors, nor published by Oyez.
Series III: Press Ephemera (undated, 1965-1986) consists of press ephemera, including advertising materials and review articles not related to specific Oyez publications.
Series IV: Business Records (1964-1981) is made up of business records, largely consisting of sales ledgers and receipts.
Series V: Printing Blocks (undated) comprises one box of wood block engravings utilized in the printing of various Oyez projects.
Related Material
Archives and Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to twentieth century American poetry, including the personal papers of Charles Olson and a vast array of literary magazines. Another related collection is the Penmaen Press Records, which focuses on another small press that produced high quality literary editions in small print runs. See also the Samuel and Ann Charters Archives of African American Venacular Music ("Charters Collection"), Ann Charters Papers, Larry Eigner Papers, Vincent Ferrini Papers, and the David Kheridan Papers. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
Collection processed and reorganized by ASC staff, focusing around project records, correspondence, and business records.
Separated Material
Monographs and serials have been cataloged. Please consult the Libraries online catalog for current titles and call numbers or ask at the reference desk for the current list.
Bibliography
Oyez: The Authorized Checklist, Berkeley, California: Dave Bohn, 1997.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Creeley, Robert, 1926-; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-; Everson, William, 1912-; Levertov, Denise, 1923-; Meltzer, David.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Norbert, Mary.; Hawley, Robert.
Subjects:
Little presses--California.; Publishers and publishing--California.; Authors and publishers--United States.; American literature--California.; American literature--20th century.; Authors, American--20th century.; Poets, American--20th century.; American poetry--20th century; American poetry--California.; Poetry--Editing.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Financial Records.; Audio cassettes.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Books.; Engravings.; Sketches.; Drawings.; Posters.
Occupations:
Publisher.; Editor.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection purchased from Serendipity Books between 1976 and 1977 in several installments.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Project Records,undated, 1963-1987
  - Broadsides,1964-1965
    - Bronk, William
      - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1:1)
      - "The Cipher", typed MS, proofs, ca. 1965 (Box 16:427)
    - Creeley, Robert
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:2)
      - "Two Poems", typed MS, proofs, correspondence, 2964 (Box 16:428)
    - Duncan, Robert
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:3)
      - "Wine", typed MS, proof, press proofs, 1964 (Box 16:429)
      - "Up Rising", proof copies, 1965 (Box 16:438)
    - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus)
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:4)
      - "The Rose of Solitude" correspondence, notes, proofs, 1964 (Box 16:430)
    - Ginsberg, Allen
      - "Kraj Majales", proof copies, ca. 1965 (Box 16:437)
    - Levertov, Denise
      - Correspondence (Box 1:5)
      - "City Psalm", typed MS, proofs, 1964 (Box 16:431)
    - McClure, Michael
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:6)
      - "Two for Bruce Conner", typed MS, proofs, correspondence, 1964 (Box 16:432)
    - Meltzer, David
      - "The Blackest Rose", broadside w/correction, typescript, galley proof corrected by author, correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:7)
      - "The Blackest Rose", typed MS, proofs, correspondence, 1964 (Box 16:433)
    - Miles, Josephine
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:8)
      - "In Identity", typed MS, proofs, 1964 (Box 16:434)
    - Olson, Charles
      - Correspondence (envelopes), 1964 (Box 1:9)
      - "Signature to Petition", typed MS, proofs, 1964 (Box 16:435)
    - Snyder, Gary
      - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1:10)
      - "Hop, Skip, and Jump", typed MS, proof copies, ca. 1964 (Box 16:436)
    - Additional materials -- Kenneth Patchen, Marianne Moore, sales materials and notices, 1964-1965 (Box 1:11)
    - Broadside Permission Slips, 1965 (Box 1:12)
  - Alexander, D. Not A Word
    - first galleys, corrected by author, ca. 1968 (Box 1:13)
    - typescript, with some corrections, ca. 1966 (Box 1:14)
    - galleys, contract, correspondence, 1966-1968, 1976 (Box 1:15)
  - Blazek, Douglas Flux and Reflux
    - correspondence, 2 sets galleys, 2 sets page proofs, cover design, notes, 1 pc. original art, 1969-1970 (Box 1:16)
    - blank dummy, set of F & G proofs (with cover proof), 1970 (Box 1:17)
    - Secondary correspondence (Cranium Press), 1966-1972 (Box 1:18)
  - Boar, Gerald (Borregard, Ebbe) Thirteen Sonnets
    - 1 set corrected galleys, 1 page partial proofs, 2 envelopes, 1969 (Box 1:19)
  - Brugnola, Orlanda King of Thornbushes
    - correspondence, typed MS, set of galleys, 1971-1972 (Box 1:20)
    - galleys pasted into layout, set of page proofs, set of proofs bound into dummy, cover proof with proofs of preliminaries, 1972 (Box 1:21)
    - copy of typed MS, ca. 1971 (Box 1:22)
    - correspondence (includes correspondence relating to Brugnola and Richard Korn), 1971-1973 (Box 1:23)
    - photo by Allen Say, used for frontispiece, ca. 1972 (Box 17:461)
  - Canan, Janice Of Your Seed
    - finished copy of book, typed MS, correspondence, ca. 1974-1983 (Box 1:24)
    - design materials, photocopy of paste-ups, 1977 (Box 1:25)
    - production paste-ups, 1977 (Box 17:458)
  - Cebulski, Frank Corm
    - typed MS, MS of essay by David Wyatt, set of galleys, printer's notes and designs, correspondence, 1974 (Box 1:26)
    - 4 sets of page proofs, undated (Box 1:27)
    - cover layout, 1974 (Box 17:462)
  - Cebulski, Frank Mediterranean Sonnets
    - Typed MS (longer version), ca. 1975 (Box 1:28)
    - Typed MS, 1 pc. correspondence, 2 copies of promotional booklet printing 2 of the sonnets, 1975-1976 (Box 1:29)
  - Charters, Ann / Charters, Samuel
    - Secondary Correspondence, 1969-1976 (Box 1:30)
  - Charters, Ann Olson/Melville: A Study in Affinity
    - galleys, early blank dummy, photograph prints, correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1:31)
    - photocopy of MSS, publicity mailing, 1968 (Box 1:32)
    - copy of finished book (hardcover) w/ marginalia and inscription to Olson from Ann Charters, 1968 (Box 1:33)
    - Photos of Charles Olson, ca. 1968 (Box 16:439)
    - Production materials, page proofs, ca. 1968 (Box 16:440)
  - Charters, Samuel To This Place
    - correspondence, cover proof, set of page proofs (cut and gathered), 1969 (Box 1:34)
  - Charters, Samuel Days
    - Days, 1965-1966 (Box 1:35)
    - trade edition in wrappers, first corrected galleys, cover proof, correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1:36)
  - Charters, Samuel "Looking for Michael McClure at the Corner of Haight and Ashbury"
    - Typed MSS, first edition of broadside, photo proof of wrapper, 1967 (Box 1:37)
    - photo montage of McClure by Dorothy Hawley, ca. 1967 (Box 17:444)
  - Charters, Samuel Some Poems/Poets
    - one set galleys, 1970 (Box 1:38)
    - Photos by Ann Charters, ca. 1971 (Box 2:39)
    - set of page proofs with printing notes, review, 1971-1972 (Box 2:40)
    - cover layout materials, ca. 1967 (Box 17:443)
  - Charters, Samuel As I Stand At This Window
    - Typed MSS, corrected galleys, proofs pasted into dummy, proof copy of book, hand-sewn copy of book, 1970 (Box 2:41)
  - Charters, Samuel From A Swedish Notebook
    - review, cover photos, printer's correspondence, 1975 (Box 2:42)
  - Charters, Samuel In Lagos
    - typed MSS with printing marks, copy of galleys with corrections, copy of proofs, folded proof set, correspondence, design materials, ca. 1976 (Box 2:43)
    - production layout, 1976 (Box 17:442)
  - Charters, Samuel Of Those Who Died
    - page proofs, printer's correspondence, 1980 (Box 2:44)
  - Charters, Samuel A Note on the Varieties of Locust
    - two copies of finished pamphlet, one is handsewn, 1987 (Box 2:45)
  - Clark, Naomi Burglaries and Celebrations
    - Copy of typed MS, 1976-1977 (Box 2:46)
    - Correspondence (includes promotional flyers), printer's correspondence, review, 1975-1984 (Box 2:47)
    - paste-up dummy, 1977 (Box 2:48)
    - set of F & G proofs with dust jacket proof, cover paste-up, photo negatives, copy of 'corrected' MSS, 1977 (Box 2:49)
  - Cody's Books "Checklists of Separate Publications of Poets at the First Berkeley Poetry Conference
    - copy of not-for-sale publication, page proofs bound as dummy, 1965 (Box 2:50)
  - Cook, Albert S.
    - Correspondence, Poetry Typed MSS (not published by Oyez), 1966-1967 (Box 2:51)
  - Dean, Robert Dinner at Mme.
    - galleys, proofs, cover proof, review, 1 pc. printer's correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2:52)
  - Dijkstra, Bram Faces in Skin
    - typescripts, galleys, sketch, ca. 1965 (Box 2:53)
  - di Prima, Diane
    - Secondary Correspondence, 1968-1976 (Box 2:54)
  - di Prima, Diane Kerhonkson Journal, 1966
    - page proofs with printer's notes, correspondence, 1971 (Box 2:55)
  - Divinelle (?) Colonial History of San Francisco
    - printer's correspondence discussing payment difficulties (work not published by Oyez) (Box 2:56)
  - Duncan, Robert "My Mother Would Be A Falconress"
    - Galley page (not published as standalone poem by Oyez), undated (Box 2:57)
  - Duncan, Robert Medea at Kolchis: The Maiden Head
    - contract, galley sets, proofs, 1965 (Box 2:58)
    - correspondence, unbound copy of first edition, review, 1965 (Box 2:59)
    - page proofs, 1 pc. correspondence, 1965 (Box 2:60)
  - Duncan, Robert The Years as Catches
    - Correspondence from Denise Levertov and Charles Olson (includes Hawley's translation of Olson's script and Olson's corrections), 1966 (Box 2:61)
    - Correspondence from Duncan, TSS of select poems, 1966 (Box 2:62)
    - partial proofs and galleys, cover design, production correspondence, 1966 (Box 2:63)
    - page proofs and first galleys, 1966 (Box 2:64)
    - galleys and second galleys with Duncan's corrections, 1966 (Box 2:65)
    - ephemera (broadside announcement), 1966 (Box 2:66)
    - secondary correspondence regarding royalties, reviews, contract, 1966-1971 (Box 2:67)
  - Duncan, Robert Of the War
    - typescript with corrections, galleys, first page proofs with corrections, page proofs, 1967 (Box 2:68)
    - typescript with corrections, galleys, first page proofs with corrections, page proofs, 1967 (Box 2:69)
  - Duncan, Robert Bending the Bow
    - 1 pc. correspondence, empty envelope with design notes, flyer advertising reading by Duncan, ca. 1967 (Box 2:70)
  - Duncan, Robert "Program Notes and Reminiscences"
    - printer's correspondence with estimate (project never completed), 1969 (Box 2:71)
  - Dusenberry, Gail The Mark
    - correspondence, Photocopy of typed MSS, contract, 1966 (Box 2:72)
    - corrected galleys, page proofs corrected and stapled, 1966-1967 (Box 2:73)
  - Dusenberry, Gail (Chiarrello, Gail ) The Bhangra Dance
    - Correspondence, galleys, galleys, proof of variant title design, copy of book as published, 1967-1970 (Box 2:74)
  - Dusenberry, Gail "The Sea-Gull"
    - correspondence, proof, dummy, 1 copy of Oyez 1968 Christmas card, 1968 (Box 2:75)
  - Edelman, Richard The Wedding Feast
    - typed MSS, typed MSS of introduction by Denise Levertov, blank dummy, 2 sets page proofs, printer's copy of finished book, 1970 (Box 2:76)
    - Correspondence, includes 1 pc. correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2:77)
  - Eigner, Larry Selected Poems, (Ed. by Samuel Charters and Andrea Wyatt)
    - correspondence from Eigner, printer's correspondence, photo, 1969-1972 (Box 3:78)
    - TSS of poems (some photocopy copies of poems), TSS of afterward, ca. 1971 (Box 3:79)
    - page proofs with printer's notes, 1971 (Box 3:80)
    - set of page proofs, 1971 (Box 3:81)
    - proof copy in orange wrappers, 1971 (Box 3:82)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Single Source
    - galleys, drawings for cover design, TSS of intro. by Robert Duncan, correspondence, review, publicity mailing, 1966 (Box 3:83)
    - gathered page proofs, 1966 (Box 3:84)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus)
    - secondary correspondence regarding reprints, copyright, press release for reading tour, 1966-1967 (Box 3:85)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus)
    - sampling of reviews, Spanish translation of "The Rose of Solitude" by Catherine Rodriguez, ca. 1966 (Box 17:450)
    - William Everson (Brother Antoninus) - mounted oversize photos of Everson, undated (Box 17:451)
    - correspondence, clippings, TSS of press release relating to Everson's wedding, TSS of untitled sequence to Susana to be read at Everson's final reading before his marriage, 1969-1970 (Box 4:107)
    - galleys for article "Hayden Carruth: The New England Tradition" (not published by Oyez), ca. 1970 (Box 4:109)
    - Ephemera -- flyer for course taught by Everson called "Birth of a Poet" with correspondence verso, 1971 (Box 4:111)
    - foldered listing of Everson MSS from 1949-1969, signed by Everson, ca. 1971 (Box 4:112)
    - unbound catalogue of Everson MSS, ca. 1971 (Box 4:113)
    - photocopy of unbound, unpaged catalogue of Everson's MSS, ca. 1971 (Box 5:114)
    - Ephemera relating to the sale of Everson's archive, correspondence from Everson, 1971, 1974 (Box 5:129)
    - Ephemera of clippings sent by Everson to Hawley, 1966-1975 (Box 5:130)
    - Photographs of Everson (includes pictures from Everson's 60th birthday party, undated, 1972 (Box 5:131)
    - Ephemera, photocopy of "The Firebreak", copies of clippings, picnic flyers, 1976 (Box 5:132)
    - Ephemera, includes correspondence regarding exhibit of Everson materials, clippings regarding Santa Cruz Poetry Carnival, 1976 (Box 5:133)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) In The Fictive Wish
    - galleys cut and corrected by Everson, partial page proofs, cloth sample, correspondence, prospectus, 1967 (Box 3:86)
    - original TSS, carbon TSS, first page proofs, ca. 1967 (Box 3:87)
    - 2 sets first galleys, 1 set corrected by Everson, 1967 (Box 3:88)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Bride of the Southwind (by Robinson Jeffers, intro. by Everson, pub. by Cayucas Books)
    - multiple sets of folded page proofs, undated (Box 3:89)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Robinson Jeffers: Fragments of an Older Fury
    - early version TSS, copies of Everson's poem on Jeffers ("A Memorial for Robinson Jeffers"), ca. 1963-1965 (Box 3:90)
    - galleys, 1967 (Box 3:91)
    - cut galleys, 1967 (Box 3:92)
    - TSS (photocopy?) with corrections, includes 14 pp. of "inserts", ca. 1967 (Box 3:93)
    - TSS (copy) with 14 pp. of "inserts", with corrections, ca. 1967 (Box 3:94)
    - First galleys (2 sets) with corrections, 1967 (Box 3:95)
    - Page proofs, fourth galleys, 1967 (Box 4:96)
    - Second galleys (2 sets) with corrections, 1967 (Box 4:97)
    - Third galleys, with corrections, set of final galleys, 1967 (Box 4:98)
    - page proofs, 1967 (Box 4:99)
    - production materials, partial galleys, typeface samples, drafts of index and acknowledgements, 1967 (Box 4:100)
    - folded page proofs, lacking front matter and index, 1967 (Box 4:101)
    - photos of Jeffers and Everson, dust jacket proof and other dustjacket materials, 1967 (Box 4:102)
    - correspondence, follow-up correspondence regarding reviews, 1968 (Box 4:103)
    - jacket proofs on aluminum sheets, ca. 1968 (Box 17:452)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) The Last Crusade
    - materials regarding Antoninus reading tour, 1969 (Box 4:104)
    - set of unbound page proofs, design notes, rough page proofs, 1969 (Box 4:105)
    - TSS of poem and 'Note', galleys, notes, correspondence, 1969 (Box 4:106)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) The City Does Not Die
    - galleys, photocopy of TSS, 1969 (Box 4:108)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Californians (by Robinson Jeffers, intro. by Everson)
    - TSS by Everson, galleys of intro. by Everson, 1 p. correspondence, 1971 (Box 4:110)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Archetype West
    - TSS with corrections, 1971 (Box 5:115)
    - partial TSS, 1 pc. correspondence, 1971 (Box 5:116)
    - photocopy of first galleys (corrected by Hawley), includes TSS of revised section, 1975 (Box 5:117)
    - photocopy of revised galleys, ca. 1975 (Box 5:118)
    - correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 5:119)
    - advance copy bound from photocopy of proofs, 1976 (Box 5:120)
    - sample boards for hardcover bindings, copy of jacket proof, ca. 1976 (Box 5:121)
    - photocopy of proofs with corrections, TSS of end notes, 1976 (Box 5:122)
    - correspondence, printer's bills, review clippings, 1975-1977 (Box 5:123)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) River-Root
    - set of F & G proofs (trade edition), extra cover proof, dummy for paperback edition, 1 pc., Correspondence, 1976 (Box 5:126)
    - dummy with printing instructions, camera ready paste-up, 1976 (Box 5:127)
    - set of F & G proofs, paper samples, 1976 (Box 5:128)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus) Earth Poetry
    - galleys, ca. 1980 (Box 5:134)
    - flyer, correspondence, printer's bills, 1980 (Box 5:135)
  - Fabilli, Mary The Old Ones
    - TSS, galley proofs, partial page proofs, contract, correspondence, author's paste-up, 1965-1966 (Box 6:136)
  - Fabilli, Mary Aurora Bligh and Early Poems
    - TSS used for typesetting (includes copies and paste-ups), ca. 1968 (Box 6:137)
    - 3 sets galleys, correspondence, ca. 1968 (Box 6:138)
    - 2 sets of rough page proofs, ca. 1968 (Box 6:139)
    - final page proofs, correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 6:140)
  - Fabilli, Mary The Animal Kingdom
    - correspondence, printer's correspondence, 2 copies of broadside poem used for promotion, 1972-1975 (Box 6:141)
  - Fabilli, Mary
    - Secondary Correspondence, 1969-1987 (Box 6:142)
  - Garcia, Luis Beans
    - Original TSS (bound in hardcover), ca. 1976 (Box 6:143)
    - 2 copies of TSS (one with printer's notes), ca. 1976 (Box 6:144)
    - printer's bill, layout materials, copy of camera-ready proofs, 1976 (Box 6:145)
    - production paste-up, 1976 (Box 17:455)
  - Ginsberg, Allen "Kraj Majales"
    - photostat of TSS, 1965 (Box 6:146)
    - galley proofs, TSS, correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 6:147)
  - Gitin, David Legwork